老天
Oh, God!
现在做这个有点太早了吧
It's a little early, isn't it?
继续睡吧  我不需要你醒着才能做
Go back to sleep. I don't need you awake for this.
亲爱的  今天是平安夜
Honey, it's Christmas Eve.
你要一整天都耗在那玩意儿上吗
Are you gonna spend all day on that thing?
我发过誓了
I made a promise.
没错
Yes!
去年圣诞节  菲尔买了一台椭圆健身机
Last Christmas, Phil got an elliptical machine
还发誓要在一年内走完
and vowed to walk the equivalent
相当于从我们家到加拿大的公里数
of our house to Canada in one year.
我这身材可不是说有就有的  女士们
This body doesn't just happen, ladies.
如果他做不到
If he didn't make it,
卧室里不准再放任何机器
no machine in the bedroom.
除了我这台机器  女士们
Except for this machine in the bedroom, ladies.
这些女士们到底是谁
Who are these ladies?
菲尔  放弃吧
Oh, Phil, give it up.
那你一定乐开花了吧
Oh, you would love that, wouldn't you?
我就快到达加拿大边境了
Just when I'm so close to the Canadian border,
都能闻到培根的香味
I can smell the bacon
还有定价合理的药品了
and the reasonably priced medications.
老妈  这是外婆寄给你的
Mom, this came for you from nana.
不知道为什么她每年都要费劲包装一下
I don't know why she bothers to wrap it every year.
内容永远不变  拖鞋
It's always the same thing -- slippers.
谁知道呢  说不定她今年会给你个惊喜
You never know. She might surprise you this year.
你有没有兴趣
Would you care to take a visit
逛逛冷漠母亲博物馆
to the museum of maternal indifference?
小心点
Watch it!
小心
Oh, careful!
非要现在就搬到楼下吗
You guys are really moving her downstairs right now?
上班不会迟到吗
Aren't you gonna be late for work?
他们不会在圣诞前夕开除精灵的
They're not gonna fire an elf on Christmas Eve.
我以为不放鞋子  这柜子能轻点呢
Ugh, I thought this would be lighter without my shoes on it.
等你整理好房间
You know, once you set up your room,
可以放些书上去
you could put books on this.
鞋架上放书
Books...on a shoe shelf.
想什么呢
Right.
-你不反驳一下吗  -我太开心了
- You're not gonna jump on that? - I'm just too happy!
今天过后
After today,
我房间里就不会再有人到处乱扔衣服
there'll be no more clothes thrown everywhere,
不会有人打好几个小时的电话
no more hour-long phone calls
全程只会说"不可能"
where all she says is "No way."
你们决定今天分开住
I think it's a little sad
我觉得有点悲伤啊
that you guys are doing this today.
我记得你们以前总是
I remember when you used to get
在平安夜睡同一张床
into the same bed on Christmas Eve
然后一起聊你们将得到的礼物
and talk about all the presents you were gonna get.
今天搬再合适不过了
It's a perfect day for it!
等我明天在我自己的房间醒来
When I wake up in my own room tomorrow,
我会感谢我获得独立
I'm going to be giving thanks for my independence.
那不正是圣诞节的意义所在吗
And isn't that what Christmas is all about?
真的吗  什么都不说吗
Seriously? Nothing?
m 20 0 l 209 0 b 218 0 229 11 229 20 l 229 209 b 229 218 218 228 209 228 l 20 228 b 11 228 0 218 0 209 l 0 20 b 0 11 11 0 20 0
m 325 0 l 355 0 l 332 47 l 354 47 l 399 136 l 369 136 l 328 53 l 288 136 l 257 136 l 325 0 m 467 0 l 497 0 l 474 47 l 496 47 l 541 136 l 511 136 l 470 53 l 430 136 l 399 136 l 467 0 m 545 1 l 583 1 l 583 14 l 568 14 l 568 19 l 583 19 l 583 30 l 568 30 l 568 34 l 599 34 l 599 30 l 583 30 l 583 19 l 599 19 l 599 14 l 583 14 l 583 1 l 611 1 b 616 1 622 6 622 10 l 622 36 l 652 0 l 678 0 l 644 41 l 622 41 l 622 47 l 596 47 l 597 54 l 625 54 l 625 68 l 541 68 l 541 54 l 572 54 l 571 47 l 545 47 l 545 1 m 583 72 l 583 85 l 569 85 l 569 90 l 598 90 l 598 85 l 583 85 l 583 72 l 611 72 b 615 72 621 78 621 82 l 653 44 l 678 44 l 644 86 l 621 86 l 621 103 l 597 103 l 597 136 l 570 136 l 564 126 l 562 136 l 542 136 l 548 107 l 568 107 l 565 121 l 571 121 l 571 103 l 547 103 l 547 72 l 583 72 m 600 107 l 620 107 l 624 124 l 653 89 l 679 89 l 642 136 l 615 136 l 618 132 l 606 132 l 600 107 m 689 0 l 716 0 l 721 15 l 732 15 l 732 30 l 718 56 l 731 56 l 735 100 l 721 100 l 717 59 l 714 64 l 714 136 l 693 136 l 693 79 l 676 79 l 707 30 l 679 30 l 679 15 l 694 15 l 689 0 m 738 0 l 804 0 b 807 0 813 6 813 9 l 813 87 l 794 87 l 794 14 l 756 14 l 756 87 l 763 77 l 763 21 l 787 21 l 787 91 l 798 91 l 798 120 l 820 120 l 812 136 l 778 136 l 778 90 l 748 136 l 723 136 l 756 87 l 738 87 l 738 0 m 257 151 l 275 151 l 297 182 l 319 151 l 337 151 l 304 197 l 304 227 l 290 227 l 290 197 l 257 151 m 337 151 l 355 151 l 377 182 l 399 151 l 417 151 l 384 197 l 384 227 l 370 227 l 370 197 l 337 151 m 425 192 l 447 192 b 445 181 427 181 425 192 l 410 192 b 414 162 458 162 462 192 l 462 206 l 425 206 b 425 210 429 212 433 213 l 462 213 l 462 227 l 433 227 b 412 227 408 203 410 192 m 462 151 l 532 151 l 532 165 l 504 165 l 504 227 l 489 227 l 489 165 l 462 165 l 462 151 m 580 172 l 580 186 l 549 186 b 543 186 543 192 549 192 l 565 192 b 589 192 589 227 565 227 l 532 227 l 532 213 l 565 213 b 570 213 570 206 565 206 l 549 206 b 524 206 524 172 549 172 l 580 172 m 592 213 l 606 213 l 606 227 l 592 227 l 592 213 m 639 172 l 665 172 l 665 186 l 639 186 b 623 186 623 213 639 213 l 665 213 l 665 227 l 639 227 b 603 227 603 172 639 172 m 700 184 b 722 184 722 215 700 215 l 700 229 b 740 229 740 170 700 170 b 660 170 660 229 700 229 l 700 215 b 680 215 680 184 700 184 m 737 172 l 782 172 b 803 172 813 177 813 198 l 813 228 l 799 228 l 799 198 b 799 186 793 187 782 187 l 782 228 l 768 228 l 768 187 l 752 187 l 752 228 l 737 228 l 737 172
m 115 64 l 115 35 l 171 0 l 177 0 l 133 46 l 143 52 l 179 0 l 184 0 l 159 63 l 229 107 l 229 182 l 145 96 l 135 122 l 207 227 l 137 227 l 115 172 l 115 93 l 126 76 l 115 64 l 104 76 l 115 93 l 115 172 l 93 227 l 23 227 l 95 122 l 84 96 l 0 182 l 0 107 l 70 63 l 45 0 l 50 0 l 87 52 l 97 46 l 52 0 l 59 0 l 115 35
m 71 60 b 71 0 161 0 161 60 b 161 120 71 120 71 60
本字幕由人人影视字幕组翻译
禁止用作任何商业盈利行为
■
翻译：小饭  冰蓝  小牛仔裤  四方虾  丁小七
时间轴：加森  浓子    校对：olivia_xuxu   后期&总监：瓜瓜
家  庭
摩  登
第五季 第十集
这是你曾祖母的菜谱
This is your great-grandmother's recipe.
如果她现在能看到你
If she could see you now...
她会死第二次的  因为你弄错了
...she would die again, because you're doing it wrong!
我母亲来这里一星期了
My mother has been here all week.
我非常爱她  但你也知道常言说
I love her very much, but you know what they say --
客人待三天就开始招人烦[发臭]了
house guests start to stink after three days,
就跟尸体一样
like dead bodies.
那是什么玩意儿
What the hell is that?
光纤圣诞树
A fiber-optic tree.
这比用真正的树对环境有利
It's way better for the environment than a real one.
但对我家客厅这个环境就不利
Not if the environment is my living room.
我承认  这得适应一段时间
Look, I admit, it takes some getting used to,
但就像希腊酸奶一样
but so did greek yogurt.
我现在都记不清原来的酸奶是什么味道了
Now I can't even remember how the old stuff tastes.
人们为什么总是改变不需要改变的东西
Why do we keep changing things that don't need changing?
过圣诞节就得有真正的圣诞树  蛋酒
Christmas is real trees and eggnog,
佩里・科莫还有高保真音响突然的巨响
Perry Como and bing on the hi-fi.
你这是在瞎掰
Now you're just making up words.
我这是在表明立场
I'm drawing a line in the sand.
我们马上去找一棵真正的树
We're gonna get a real tree,
然后像我小时候那样砍倒它
and we're gonna cut it down like I did when I was a kid.
跟我来
Follow me.
老爸
Hi, dad.
没空聊天  我在拯救圣诞节
Can't talk. Saving Christmas.
再次感谢你能来
Hi. Thank you again for coming.
不客气  我超爱看孩子
No problem. I love babysitting!
太好了  我们要去办点事儿
Good! We're going to run some quick errands.
等等  如果你要带走乔
Wait, if you're taking Joe --
你好啊  克莱尔
Hola, Claire!
大概四点左右回来  她很挑剔她的水瓶
Around 4:00, she gets fussy for her bottle.
莉莉  你知道今天我为什么能
Lily, do you know why I'm able to relax
这么放松地看报纸吗
and read this paper today?
因为你没有工作吗
Because you don't have a job?
告诉你  再过几天我就要开始新工
FYI, I am starting a new job in exactly t--
算了  我不再重复了
No. We're not doing this again.
是因为我提前计划好了
It's because I planned ahead.
我几周前就完成了圣诞购物
I finished my Christmas shopping weeks ago.
保持紧张忙碌非常重要
It's important to keep busy.
偶尔休息一下也非常正常
I-it is perfectly normal to take some downti--
不  算了
No. No!
好吧
Okay.
我把胡娇的派对指南打印出来了
I printed out the directions to Pepper's party.
现在改名叫"十二圣诞基佬"了
We're calling it "The 12 Gays of Christmas" now.
我们说服他没用
Oh, just be thankful
"快乐基男"已经要谢天谢地了
we talked him out of "Feliz Navidude."
好了  亲爱的  快吃完早饭
Okay, honey, finish your breakfast
我们要去帮我们的同胞了
so we can go help our fellow man!
去慈善活动上参与一小时  最多
One hour at this charity event, max.
我吃不了了
I can't eat.
就要得到我的胖胖狗之家了  我好激动
I'm too excited to get my Puppy Pound.
我  抱歉  你说你的什么
I'm -- I'm sorry. Your what?
胖胖狗之家里有六只小狗
Puppy pounds have six puppies
每只都有网络档案
with online profiles.
上网前要寻求家长同意
Ask your parents before using the Internet.
亲爱的  你从没提过什么胖胖狗之家啊
Honey, you never mentioned a-a-a puppy pound.
-她在说什么  -礼物单上没有这个
- What is she talking about? - I-it's not on your list.
有啊  在这儿  "胖胖狗之家"
Yes, it is. "Puppy Pound."
不是吧  她把"P"写反了
Oh, no! She put a "P" backwards.
而且亲爱的  "Pound"里有字母"u"
And, honey, there's a "u" in "Pound."
-这写的是"古比鱼池"  -古比鱼池
- This says "Guppy Pond"! - Guppy Pond!
什么是古比鱼池
What is a Guppy Pond?
这是  有史以来最酷的礼物
It's only the -- the coolest gift ever!
我要胖胖狗之家
I want a Puppy Pound.
亲爱的  今天是圣
Um, honey, it's C--
好了
Okay.
我不是要指责谁
I am not pointing fingers,
但我们女儿在清单上
but our daughter had
明明白白列出了一样东西
exactly one thing on her list,
但某人却没有买到
and someone didn't get it,
所以某人现在得去商场
so someone needs to go to the mall.
你在"指"责我
You're pointing fingers.
不  这还是个"1"
No. It's still a "1."
只不过它偷懒睡着了
It just fell asleep on the job.
健身日志  12月24日
Ellipticaler's log, 12/24.
距离加拿大边界还有10英里
10 miles from Canadian border.
情绪高涨  精力充沛
Spirits -- high. Stamina -- strong.
必须再来一剂大腿润滑油
Must get another application of thigh lube.
很好  卢克
Oh, good. Luke.
爸爸  走钢丝时我支持你
Dad, I was with you on the tightrope.
吃鸡翅比赛时  我是你的搭档
I was your wing man in the wing-eating competition.
但这次我不愿意陪着你
But I'm not feeling this one.
你要错过平安夜了
You're missing Christmas Eve.
有些东西比圣诞节更重要  儿子
There's something more important than Christmas, son
那就是自尊
-- pride.
如果我到不了加拿大
If I don't make it to Canada,
你妈妈获胜了  这宝贝
your mom wins, and this baby
明天一早就会被丢进车库里
ends up in the garage first thing in the morning.
我们家车库吗
Our garage?
我负责回收垃圾
I'm in charge of the recycling.
我该在周四早晨六点从车库
I'm supposed to bring it from the garage to the curb
拿出垃圾放在马路边
by 6:00 A.M. Thursday morning.
我也许错过了几周
I may have missed a few weeks.
该死
Shoot!
也许不止几周
Maybe more than a few weeks.
过了一阵子  垃圾堆越来越大
After a while, the pile just got so big,
我不能在前一晚把垃圾都搬出去
I couldn't bring it out the night before
不然人们会问问题的
or people would ask questions.
我可不需要人们问问题
I don't need people asking questions.
你说得对  你得完成
Then you're right! You've got to finish!
你在车库里可用不上这个  那里风太大
You'll never use this thing in the garage! It's too drafty!
所以我才要去加拿大啊  儿子
That's why I'm going to Canada, buddy --
躲开大风
to avoid the draft!
不行
No.
找到了
Bang.
我知道我们已经走了一小时了  但是
I know we've been hiking for an hour, but...
这棵树多美啊  真是太值得了  对吧
worth it when you look at this beauty, huh?
所以不要砍伐你看到的第一棵树
That's why you don't cut down the first tree you see.
这就是我们看到的第一棵树
This is literally the first tree we saw.
我们的车就停在那里
There's our car.
不  我们是从那边开始的
No, we started that way.
所以你的意思是
So, you're arguing
我们围着地球绕了一圈吗
that we walked entirely around the earth?
把斧子给我
Give me the ax.
别那样看着我
Don't give me that look.
树就像女人一样
Trees are like women.
你得多费功夫  才能得到最好的
The best ones make you work a little bit harder.
她只是没那么喜欢你
She's just not that into you.
-就是啊  -抱歉花了这么长时间
- I know! - Sorry it too long!
没事啦
Oh, it's fine.
克莱尔和我聊得很开心
Claire and I were having a nice time catching up.
真抱歉我迟到了
I am really sorry that I am late.
你才不抱歉
No, you're not.
的确如此
No, I'm not.
没关系啦
Mm-hmm. It's fine.
希望我这个话唠没烦到皮娜
Just hope I didn't talk Pilar's ear off!
没有啦
No!
我喜欢听你聊你的家人
I love hearing about your family
和你重大新工作的事
and your big, new job!
这工作不算重大啦
Oh, well, it's -- it's not such a big job.
我只是在为我老爸工作而已
I mean, I'm really just working for my dad.
但你有努力工作啊
But you're working hard.
我为你感到骄傲
I'm proud of you.
-看起来怎么样  -完美
- How do they look? - Ooh! Perfect!
-太棒了  -你是超棒的学生
- Yes. - You are a wonderful student.
-谢谢  -这是我祖母教给我妈妈的
-Thank you.  -My grandmother taught my mother.
我妈妈又教给了我
My mother taught me.
现在我教给了克莱尔
And now, I teach Claire.
别谦虚啦
And don't be so modest.
我尊重那种能养育家庭
I respect a woman who can raise a family
同时又有全职工作的女人
and have a full-time job.
你能相信吗  在周五
Can you believe that on Fridays,
她们都没必要盛装打扮
they don't even have to dress up?
尝尝  尝尝
Taste. Taste. Taste.
有时她们甚至穿运动裤哦
Sometimes, they even wear sweatpants.
你想舔一舔面糊吗
Would you like to lick the batter?
超想
Yes! Oh, yes!
-我也想  -不行
- Me, too! - No, no, no!
帮忙的人才能吃到
Helpers only.
规矩不是我定的
I don't make the rules.
莉莉  装饰品真漂亮
Oh, Lily, what a beautiful ornament!
这会让一个小朋友很开心的
That's gonna make a little kid very happy.
等等  我不能留着吗
Wait. I don't get to keep this?
为什么我还做得这么费力
Why am I killing myself?
好了  孩子们
Okay, kids!
北极有人来探望我们了
We've got a visitor from the North Pole,
而且他带了礼物哦
and he brought presents!
喂  怎么样
Hey! Hey. How's it going?
到处都买不到胖胖狗之家
There are no Puppy Pounds anywhere.
简直就像在1983年的平安夜寻找
It's like trying to find a Cabbage Patch Kid
椰菜娃娃一样
on Christmas Eve 1983.
还无法释怀呐
Still hurts, huh?
我把她的床都铺好了
I had her bed all made.
好吧  莉莉会难过死的
Okay. Well, Lily is gonna be devastated.
打电话问问  把我们排上预订名单
Call around. Get us on some lists.
你得做些什么
You have to do something!
我会想办法的
I'll figure it out.
募捐会怎么样
How's the fundraiser?
我在设法对付
Oh, well, I'm managing, you know.
把支票本拿来
Oh, bring the checkbook.
能看出他们准备提出重大请求的样子
You can always tell when they're gearing up for the big ask --
给了很多免费赠品
Fill you full of freebies.
我得挂了  得去帮帮别人
Oh, hey, I gotta go. Got to help somebody.
你好  经典小丑
Hi! Classic.
扔得真完美
Flawlessly executed.
如果我有一个...
If I had one...
只想让你们能笑逐颜开
Just trying to bring a smile to you folks.
-你会度过这一切的  -度过什么
- You're gonna get through this. - Get through what?
别不好意思
Don't be embarrassed.
我们都处境相同
Everyone here is in the same boat.
是吗
We are?
热可可最妙的一点
Best thing about the hot chocolate --
喝完后杯子也归我们
they let us keep the mug.
我以为这是为有需要的人募捐的慈善活动
I thought it was a charity event for the needy.
结果是让有需要人士来参加的慈善活动
Turns out, it was a charity event for the needy!
瞧  圣诞老人给了我一个胖胖狗之家
Look! Santa gave me a puppy pound!
什么  不
What? No.
我终于开心啦
I'm finally happy!
我需要给新闻报道拍张照片
I'd like a picture for the newsletter.
你可以给你妈妈看看
Oh. You can show your mommy.
我没有妈妈
I don't have a mommy.
所以我才办这活动
This is why I do this.
也许不是抽筋  可能要犯心脏病
That cramp could be a heart attack.
我要给你留下一些建议
Here's some advice I've been holding back on.
刮胡子的时候要顺着皮肤纹理刮
Always shave with the grain.
真正有本事的地产中介
No reputable talent agent
是不会一开始就谈钱的
will ever ask for money up-front.
爸  你没事的
Dad, you're fine.
卢克  我好想放弃啊
I really want to quit, Luke!
不  你可以的
No, you're gonna make it!
他根本不可能做到的
He was never gonna make it.
我只是要拖延时间
I just needed to buy some time.
你要搬的东西真够多的
That's a lot of product you're moving.
带到垃圾回收场就行了
Just bring it to a recycling place.
给了钱我才办事
Not until I get paid.
这可是人家六个星期的补贴呢
Just so you know, this is six weeks' allowance.
你家长真是酷毙了
Oh, you have the coolest parents ever.
我得知道你什么时候出发
I want to know when you're about to leave,
按一下喇叭通知我
so give me a honk.
-嘀嘀  -按汽车的喇叭
- Honk! -  From your car.
最好的名片就是有力的握手
The best business card is a firm handshake.
最好的搭讪诀窍是穿紧身工作裤
The best pick-up line is a tight pair of dockers.
最好的工作裤是...
The best dockers are --
爸爸  别说了  还有最后五英里了
Dad, save your breath! You're in the last five miles.
-我永远也跑不完了  -你当然能
- I'm never gonna make it! - Of course you are!
不过你爱怎么办怎么办吧  我还有事
Then again, do what you want. I got stuff to do.
-我要放弃了  -好吧
- I'm gonna quit. - Cool.
再失败一次又怎么样呢
What's one more failure?
你想过我们为什么要绕远去学校吗
You ever wonder why we take such a crazy route to school?
因为那样我就不用路过某些地方了
So I don't have to drive by certain places --
那个我只去过一次的长笛老师家
The flute teacher's house I went to once...
那个我只学了五大基本酱料中的两种
The French cooking academy I quit after learning
就退出了的法餐烹饪学校
only two of the five mother sauces...
那个只学了一个动作就放弃了的瑜伽教室
The hot yoga studio I left after "Happy baby."
看来是怎么也躲不过
I guess there's no avoiding
车库里这个巨大的失败了
this big failure sitting in my garage.
起来
Get up.
谢谢你  伙计  不过...
I appreciate it, buddy, but --
快起来
Get up.
我不会你说的长笛
I don't know anything about flutes
或者烹饪或者瑜伽...
or cooking or happy babies...
但我拼了老命也要让你去加拿大
But I'm damn sure getting my dad to Canada.
加油跑到终点吧
Now, mount that beast.
谢谢你  儿子
Thank you, son.
等你跑过终点开始庆祝的时候
You can thank me after you cross the finish line
再谢我
and the celebration begins.
想象一下吧
Just picture that.
我能想象到
I'm picturing it!
我真的能想象到
I'm really picturing it!
谢谢你  圣诞老人
Thanks, Santa.
好  没事
Yeah. You got it.
别忘了圣诞夫人给你的糖果棒
Don't forget a candy cane from Mrs. Claus!
我得休息会儿
Oh! I got to take a break.
-什么  -搞什么
- What? - What? What?
没关系
Um...it's okay!
谁想和我照张相呀
Does anybody want to take a picture with me?
-我想  -我是说孩子们
- I'll do it. - Oh, maybe just the kids.
-刚才怎么回事  -什么怎么回事
- What was that? - What was what?
圣诞老人不能休息
Santa doesn't take breaks.
他要去北极的
He visits the North Pole!
而且你怎么把这里弄得乱七八糟的
And why do you leave your things all over?
最后是我要打扫这里好吗
Who do you think cleans this place up?
你怎么像祥林嫂似的
Oh, you are such a nag!
我们连在过节的时候
Can't we at least
假装是幸福的一对都不行吗
act like a happy couple during the holidays?
为了孩子们
For the children!
你还喝热巧克力
Another hot chocolate?
你还想喝多少杯啊
How many more of those are you going to drink?
至少它是暖的  不像你
At least it's warm, unlike you!
圣诞老人常在外出差
He travels a lot.
圣诞夫人吃曲奇吃胖了
She's put on cookie weight.
日子不好过
It's hard.
没问题  你可以把我放在
Yes, you can put me on
"亡羊补牢礼物购买者"的名单上
the "Last-minute shoppers" waiting list.
-真行  -你也在这里啊
- Unbelievable. - Oh! Well, there he is!
乔森
H-hey, Jotham!
看来你也是
Oh, looks like someone did
临到圣诞才想起要买礼物
a little last-minute Christmas shopping.
那个赞尼尔真是幸运啊
That Zaniel's a lucky guy.
他的确很幸运
Yes, he is.
但这些是要带去胡娇的派对的
But these are for Pepper's party.
他的请柬上不是说了不要带礼物吗
His invitation said, "No gifts, please."
重复一遍那句话
Mm, say that again...
用胡娇的语气
as Pepper.
没带礼物吗
No gifts?
想不想活了
Please.
现在是平安夜的下午五点
5 o'clock, Christmas Eve,
我还得去买最完美的礼物
and I have to find a dozen perfect presents
给世界上最挑剔最尖刻的男人们
for the world's snarkiest, cattiest men...
我亲爱的朋友们
My dear, dear friends.
拉  拉  再拉
Pull! Pull! Pull!
好了  休息会儿吧
Yeah. Hey, take a break.
-这也太费时了  -本来就是
- This is taking forever. - It's supposed to.
原来我和我爸要花一整天弄倒一棵树
Took my dad and I all day to get a tree.
当终于把树砍下来的时候
And when he finally brought her down,
他会抽根雪茄来庆祝
he used to celebrate with a cigar.
我那时还是个孩子  所以就抽根香烟
I was just a kid, so I'd have a cigarette.
好了  抓住另一边
All right. Grab the other end.
这就对了
There we go.
这就进入状态了吧
Now we got a groove.
好了  这就可以...
Yeah. There we --
它就是不断
It won't budge!
这木头是他妈什么做的啊
The hell is this wood made of?
都能拿来做锯了好吗
They ought to make saws out of it!
面对现实吧  这棵树把我们打败了
Let's face it. The tree's beaten us.
我们普里契特家的人是不会半途而废的
Hey, we're Pritchetts. We don't quit.
再说了  我的工具都卡在里面
Besides, all my tools are stuck in it.
我知道该怎么办了
I got it.
非常简单的原理
It's simple physics.
给这棵树施点压
A little pressure,
它就会在我们砍的地方断掉
the thing will snap where we put the blade in.
-这不就完事了  -赶紧的吧
- Done. - Just hit the gas.
凑效了吧
It's working.
这才叫北方汉子做的发动机
That's why they call it yankee engine--
小心
Get down!
半棵树都秃了
It's bald on one side now!
没事的
It'll be fine!
两边匀一匀就好了
We'll just comb over some branches!
克莱尔  我以为你走了呢
Oh, Claire, I thought that you had left.
她本来是要走了
She was going to,
但我想让她看看没有这些头发挡着
But I wanted to show her how much better she looks
她的脸  她有多美丽动人
without this hair blocking her pretty face.
她头发确实很美
She does have beautiful hair, though.
我知道
I see.
她说什么
What did she say?
说你碰巧赶上一个好发色
That you picked a good color...
反正我觉得她是这个意思
At least, I think that's what she said
她美国口音太重
with that American accent.
你不用哄她高兴
You don't have to entertain her.
毕竟她是我妈
After all, she's my mother.
这是歌洛莉亚以前最爱吃的
Ah, these used to be Glorita's favorite!
她以前为了能多吃点常做手头倒立
She used to do headstands to get extra cookies.
至少会努力去做
At least, she'd try.
是的  真的不容易做到
Yeah, but it's not easy!
我站着的时候要保持她们坚挺都很不容易
I mean, it's hard enough to keep all this right-side up!
你可以想象倒过来会有多难
Imagine when I had to put it all right-side down!
-那太...  -天呐
- It was... - Oh, my gosh.
真不敢相信我还能做到
I can't believe I can still do it!
看呐
Look at that.
看看克莱尔  歌洛莉亚
Oh, wow. Look at Claire, Gloria!
真棒  给你两块小点心
Very good! Two cookies for you!
谢谢
Thank you!
是啊  可她需要修修脚
Uh, yeah, but she needs a pedicure.
看呐
Look at that.
你把我弄倒了
You knocked me down!
-我没有  -有  你弄的
- I did not. - Yes, you did, too!
姑娘们  姑娘们  别吵了
Girls! Girls! Girls! No need to fight.
我没有偏爱你们哪一个
I don't have a favorite.
为什么没有
Why the hell not?!
我对你们两个非常失望
I am very disappointed in both of you.
家庭成员应该用爱和尊重
Family members should treat each other
来对待彼此
with love and respect.
但克莱尔不是我们家的人
Except that Claire is not part of our family.
-闭嘴  -不不
- Cierra la boca! - No. No, no.
她说的对  除非你刚才说的就是这个
She's right-- unless that's what you just said.
我听不懂  因为我只学了法语
I can't tell, 'cause I-I only took French,
能讲一点点
And je parle un peu.
你的语调很美啊
Oh, you have a beautiful accent.
真的吗  你这么觉得吗
Really? Do you think so?
-拜托  -抱歉 我
- Ay-ya! Por favor? - I'm sorry. I...
我很嫉妒
I-I'm jealous.
克莱尔
Ay, Claire.
你也很美  个性的美
But you're beautiful, too, in your own way.
不  我不是嫉妒你
No. I'm not jealous of you.
我嫉妒你妈妈
I am jealous of how your mother
大老远从哥伦比亚来看你
comes all the way to see you from Colombia,
可我妈甚至都不愿意从她住的
When my own mother won't even get on a bus
阿尔蒙公寓坐车过来  只有三小时路程
from the Almond co-op she lives on three hours away.
她会寄礼物来的  没有吗
She sends presents, no?
有寄  但每年都一样
Yeah. It's the same thing every year.
永远是拖鞋
It's always slippers.
我为你感到难过
I am sorry.
谢谢
Thank you.
但我不该因为我妈妈不好
But I shouldn't take it out on you
就把气撒在你头上
just 'cause I have a lousy mom.
不许不尊重你妈妈
Don't disrespect your mother!
-她总这样吗  -是的
- Is she always like this? - Yes.
你就没想过也许她寄给你那样礼物
Did you-- did you ever think maybe there's a reason
是有原因的吗
she sends you that gift?
想过  因为在我8岁时
Yeah, 'cause she found something
她发现了我很喜欢的礼物
when I was 8 years old that I actually liked,
从此就再也没花心思选礼物给我
and she hasn't thought about it since.
也许她花了很多心思
Well, maybe she thinks about it a lot.
也许她记得她让你开心的那个时刻
Maybe she remembers a time when she made you happy,
她想回到过去
and she wants to go back there.
现在我好难受
Well, now I feel terrible.
我只寄给她一张电子贺卡
The only thing I sent her was an e-card.
我们都不愿意承认
We don't like to admit it...
可妈妈们永远不会忘记
But mothers never get over
女儿们离开她们的那天
the day their daughters leave them.
我们从未停止对自己的女儿的依赖
We never stop needing our little girls.
我也从未停止对你的依赖  妈妈
I will never stop needing you, mama.
你最好不要给我寄拖鞋
绝不会
很好
不好意思
Excuse me.
不好意思  精灵
Excuse me, elf,
已经过去45分钟了
it's been 45 minutes.
圣诞老人去哪了
Where's Santa?
我不知道
I don't know!
他可能忙着为世界上所有的孩子
Maybe he's a little busy making presents
做礼物呢
for every child in the world.
等一下
One second!
他人呢
Where is he?
他说他要出去买一包糖果棒
He said he was going out for a pack of candy canes.
你是指那玩意吗
You mean like those?
好了  醒醒  他不会回来了
Okay. Wake up! He is not coming back!
我们需要换回便装
We need to change into our regular clothes
溜出去
and sneak out.
我想什么呢
Who am I kidding?
我的双眼是让人过目难忘的
My eyes are unforgettable.
我连个假丈夫都留不住
I couldn't even hold on to a fake husband.
我总认为你是难相处的人
I always thought you were the tough one to live with,
可或许我才是
but maybe I am.
他们已经冲破了糖果围栏  问题大了
Okay, they've breached the jelly bean moat. This is a problem.
这是个大问题  我一直在等一个
It's a big problem. All this time, I've been waiting
能了解我的人
for a guy to see the true me,
可现在我却害怕被他看透
and now I'm scared he will.
天呐  他们打倒布利岑了
Oh, my god! They've got Blitzen!
[圣诞老人的第九只驯鹿]
我会怎么样
What's going to happen to me?
我会一直挑剔别人直到人家离开我吗
Am I just going to nitpick everyone until they leave me?
-妈妈都找到对象了  -这倒是
- Hey, mom found somebody! - That's true.
好了  听着
Okay, listen.
我们真的得离开这里
We really need to get out of here.
我只想让你知道
But I just want to let you know
你不是那么难相处 我觉得
that you weren't all bad to live with. I thought--
天呐
Oh, my god!
圣诞老人呢
Where's santa?!
只剩下一百码了
Only 100 more yards.
你就要到达了
You're just about there!
看到了吗
Can you see it?
未来真美好  满眼绿色
It's so beautiful. It's so green.
而且  好高啊
And, wow, those are high up there.
山脉吗
The mountains?
不是  还是我的短裤
No, my shorts again.
介意最后再拉它一下吗
Would you mind giving them one last tug?
你穿过边境了[越界]
You're crossing the border.
我知道  我也不好意思问出口
Yeah, I know, and I feel bad asking,
可我感觉到它紧紧地包着我
But I'm tasting cotton.
不是  你做到了  你到加拿大了
No! You did it! You're in Canada!
等等  什么
Wait. What?
我做到了  我做到了
I did it? I did it!
I did it! I did it!
我们快去告诉妈妈
Let's go tell mom!
等等
Wait.
我以前是怎么走路的
How did I used to walk?
好了  宝贝儿  快来
All right. Come on, sweetie.
我们走
Let's go.
我们提供圣诞晚餐
Uh, we're serving Christmas dinner.
不  没关系
Uh, no. That's fine.
我们必须得走了
We have to actually get going, so...
可我今天还没吃过东西呢
But I haven't eaten today.
可怜的小家伙
Oh, you poor thing!
她没关系的  没事
No, she's fine. She's fine.
他来了
Oh, there he is.
亲爱的  你这外套在哪拿的
Honey, where did you get this coat?
不好意思  孩子们
Sorry, kids.
外套和玩具好像发完了
It looks like we've run out of coats and toys.
没关系  妈妈  至少我看到礼物了
That's okay, mom. At least I got to see presents.
好了  快过来  我们走
Okay. Come on. Let's go.
我的好心人们今天过得怎么样
Hey! How are my do-gooders?
玩得开心吗
Did you have fun?
还行  上车再说 我的天啊
Yep. Talk about it in the car. Oh, my gosh.
这些是什么
What are these?
是啊  我是不是有点太疯狂了
Yeah, I went a little crazy, huh?
不  不  这是个圣诞节奇迹
No! No, no! It's a Christmas miracle!
孩子们  孩子们  谁想要礼物
Kids! Kids! Who wants presents?
小卡  你在做什么
Cam, what are you doing?
不  相信我  莉莉的礼物足够了
No, trust me. Lily has enough.
-小卡  小卡  -大家圣诞快乐
- Cam, Cam. - Everybody, Merry Christmas!
那个不可以
Oh! Not that one.
圣诞快乐
Feliz navidad!
好吧  可是那些不是给莉莉的
Okay, but those aren't for Lily.
"他与他的沐浴拖鞋"
"His-and-his shower clogs?"
这些是要带去胡娇的派对的
They're for Pepper's party.
他说过不用带礼物的
He said, "No gifts, please."
想象一下胡娇说那句话的语气
Imagine how Pepper would say that.
"喜马拉雅盐盘"是什么东西
What's a Himalayan salt plate?
你可以一边上菜一边调味
You can season your food while you serve it. Yeah.
脂肪秤
Body-fat scale?
我像你这么大的时候很想要一个
I wish I would've had one of those when I was your age.
[美国八十年代黑白片摄影大师]
-不用谢  -罗伯特・梅普尔索普是谁
- You're welcome. - Who's Robert Mapplethorp?
实际上  我得把那个拿回来 不好意思
Actually, I'm gonna need that one back. Sorry.
没关系
That's okay.
我今年真正想要的就是一个胖胖狗之家
All I really wanted this year was a Puppy Pound.
给  我的可以给你
Here. You can have mine.
可好玩了
It's really fun.
我的天啊
Oh, my gosh.
这是我见到过最感人的事了
That's the sweetest thing I've ever seen!
莉莉  宝贝儿  你这样做太好了
Lily, honey, that was so nice!
没事儿  我明天还会有一个
It's okay. I'll get one tomorrow.
那个  你知道吗  关于那个
Um, well, you know what? About that --
小卡  小卡
Cam? Cam?
是玩具店打来的
Uh, that was a t-o-y s-t-o-r-e.
-怎么了  -有人退了一个胖胖狗之家
- What? - Someone returned their Puppy Pound.
可我们在他们关门之前赶不过去
W-we can't get over there in time before the store closes!
等等  你知道谁就住那家店旁边吗
Wait, you know who lives right over there?
不  不
Oh, no. No!
马上就到
Almost there.
不
No.
不  为什么会这样
No! Why?!
为什么
Why-y-y-y-y?!
事后诸葛亮一下  那支烟是个错误
In hindsight, the cigar was a mistake.
那我们现在怎么办
So, what do we do now?
我们回家吧
We go home.
我以为普里契特家的人是不会放弃的
I thought Pritchetts never give up.
他们知道什么时候应该放手
They know when to give up,
也算是某种战胜自我
which is its own kind of victory.
-除非  -怎么了
- Unless... - what?
算了  太疯狂了
No it's crazy.
除非
Unless...
你真的想我再问一遍吗
Are you really gonna make me ask you again?
我们可以想办法给树干上的斧头施加压力
...we somehow apply pressure to the axhead already in the tree.
可以用车上的千斤顶
I bet we can use the jack from the car.
不错  向上的力可以撕裂树干
Of course. The upward motion will split the trunk. Yeah.
我们可以跟别人说我们是那么做的
We can always tell people that's how we did it.
我们就是那么做到的
That is how we did it.
人们总喜欢得到新东西
People love getting new things...
不过最好的东西背后都有个故事
But the best stuff has a story behind it.
超棒的树
Damn fine tree.
只是锯子还卡在树上
Except the saw's still stuck in the truck.
你要负责不让你弟弟靠近那个
Yeah, you're gonna want to keep your brother away from that, huh?
很多时候  只有当我们失去了之后
A lot of times, it's only after we get rid of something...
有我的位置吗
Room for me?
才意识到自己有多怀念
...that we realize how much we miss it.
真好
Oh! Nice!
干得不错  卢克
Good job, Luke!
好棒  胖胖狗之家
Yay! A Puppy Pound!
看起来没什么价值的东西
And things that seem worthless
突然就变得很有价值
suddenly turn out to be super valuable...
大家一起到圣诞树前合影
Okay, everybody, picture in front of the tree.
定好时间了  准备好了吗
Timer's set. Ready?
什么  不
What? No!
甚至是宝贵
...maybe even precious...
所以我才觉得我们也许
Which is why I thought getting rid of this stuff
不应该把这些丢掉
would be a huge mistake.
得了吧
Nice try.
你欠我们六个星期的补贴
You still owe us six weeks' allowance,
还有烟花
and the fireworks.
你居然把事情搞砸了
How could you screw this up?
你说什么
What?
我们温哥华见
I'll see you in Vancouver, eh?
不对  卢克  再学一遍口音
No. Luke, do the accent again?
你还在跑着呢
Oh, are you on that machine?
对  朱莉安娜  但跟你老公不同的是
Yes, Juliana, but unlike your husband,
我会在你反应过来之前就完事的
I'll be finished before you know it.
你知道吗  这样其实更轻松了
You know what? It's actually easier this way!
不知道能不能给这个动作申请专利
Wonder if you could patent a movement?
就叫"菲式旋转"
Call it "Fliptical" --
爸  小朋友们来要糖果了
Dad, trick or treaters!
我们的糖发完了
We're out of candy!
这个爸爸是谁
Who is this dad?
我是甘道夫
I'm Gandalf.
我来啦
Who's on?